<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on Ten thousand words...</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Home on Ten thousand words...</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 09:48:44 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mespe.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Surgery consult #1</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/surgeon1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 09:48:44 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/surgeon1/</guid><description>After eight hours in the ED, I was sent home with no diagnostic evidence as to what had caused the stomach ache. Certainly less than ideal, but I was just happy to be going home at that point.
The next day I dutifully made the appointment with my primary care doctor, which lead to a referral for a CT scan of my abdomen and a consult with a surgeon. My doctor said it was all precautionary &amp;ndash; he just wanted the images and consult with the surgeon in case the pain returned.</description></item><item><title>The tummy ache</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/the_beginning/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 15:33:25 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/the_beginning/</guid><description>About two months ago, I had a horrible tummy ache. A no-good, very bad tummy ache. It started like food poisoning, but slowly built to just pain. Pain and nothing else.
And just like that, a strange chapter of my life would kick off.
At first I tried to shrug off the pain - I certainly have had food poisoning before. My travels through China had some particularly rough moments. So I went about my life as normal.</description></item><item><title>New Direction for the Blog</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_direction/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2022 14:16:03 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_direction/</guid><description>Hello, long neglected blog!
For months and months I have not had much to write about&amp;hellip; well, that&amp;rsquo;s not exactly true. I originally envisioned this space as being primarily for more professional posts - data science, stats, sciencey stuff. But then I started co-authoring a book, and many of those thoughts were being put into the book. Or I found myself without the time to write new posts.
But I have lots I have wanted to write about, topics which are not data science, stats, sciencey stuff.</description></item><item><title>Workstation Update Pt. 2</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update_pt2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 15:19:41 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update_pt2/</guid><description>Previously, I discussed some of the reasons I was updating my computer, and what my goals for the rebuild would be - a smaller, quieter, more efficient, more powerful workstation.
There are many different ways to get to that goal. Here, I am going to talk through how I determined what path to take.
Processor This is probably the biggest determinate for the rest of the system, as it will dictate some of the other components.</description></item><item><title>Workstation Update</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 14:27:08 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update/</guid><description>Way back in 2017, I built a cheap data science rig for $600. You can read about the build here. Since that post, I added a mid-tier NVIDIA GPU for machine learning, and some hard drives for more storage. Otherwise, it&amp;rsquo;s been pretty bullet-proof for the last 3 years.
While it was a great solution for what needed at the time, eventually it&amp;rsquo;s shortcomings were increasingly obvious. Those were:
Efficiency (or lack there of): 16 cores of 2012-circa Xeon processors pulled roughly 200W on their own.</description></item><item><title>Untidy Tuedsay: Cocktails</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/untidy_cocktails/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 11:38:38 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/untidy_cocktails/</guid><description>So, one of the Tidy Tuesday challenges was brought to my attention recently due to a video of Hadley Wickam taking a swing at it.
In the video, Hadley does what he calls a hacky fix to tackle the data having fractions in the measure column, e.g.
1 1/2 oz Hadley does what many people appear to have done, which is to replace the fraction with the equivalent decimal using string replacement,</description></item><item><title>How I write an R function</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/write_a_fun/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 11:07:58 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/write_a_fun/</guid><description>One of the things that I was fortunate to learn relatively early in my R career was how to write a function. Functions allow you to avoid duplicating code, and facilitate better readability, maintenance, and testing of your code.
Over the years, how I write functions has changed. Due to an out-sized influence of one DTL, I now write my functions in a somewhat atypical style, which I thought might be worth showing.</description></item><item><title>Extract a number from a string with base R</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/num_extract/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 07:31:15 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/num_extract/</guid><description>This problem came across my desk yesterday, and I thought it was interesting and straightforward.
The problem is extracting a &amp;ldquo;group&amp;rdquo; number from the middle of a string. The strings looked like:
strings = c(&amp;#34;Group_1.Pooled&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_1.Sample_1&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_1.Sample_2&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_1.Sample_3&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_2.Pooled&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_2.Sample_1&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_2.Sample_2&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_2.Sample_3&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_3.Pooled&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_3.Sample_1&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_3.Sample_2&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_3.Sample_3&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_4.Pooled&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_4.Sample_1&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_4.Sample_2&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_4.Sample_3&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_5.Pooled&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_5.Sample_1&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_5.Sample_2&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Group_5.Sample_3&amp;#34; ) So, what is the &amp;ldquo;base R&amp;rdquo; way to do this? Turns out there are many&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Doing things the 'hard' way</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/doing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 12:18:07 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/doing/</guid><description>Wow - long time since I&amp;rsquo;ve written anything. Mostly because, with the world ending and all, I did not feel like anything I had to say was fully formed yet. Everything needed a little time to simmer.
I&amp;rsquo;ve also grown disatistfied with all the hot-takes flying around. So I decided to just shut up for a while (not that I have been a particularly prolific blogger in the before times).</description></item><item><title>Xmas Functions, revisited</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/xmas_revisited/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 09:47:01 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/xmas_revisited/</guid><description>Years ago, a friend asked me for help writing a function to do her family&amp;rsquo;s Xmas gift exchange. You can see her post on a collection of functions for this here. The basic goal here is to have a function that randomizes the names in the hat, but with the restriction that close family members (spouses) cannot draw eachother. We want to simulate the process of pulling names out of a hat where you cannot draw yourself or your partner.</description></item><item><title>Future of R (per Hadley)</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/future_of_r/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 10:03:30 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/future_of_r/</guid><description>Quartz had a pretty interesting interview with Hadley Wickham on the Future of R. While the interview was pretty short, it has many interesting tidbits about how Hadley thinks about R.
The problem with the future of R according to the tidyverse and RStudio Many of the tidyverse developers are employed by RStudio, a commercial company. It is, in many ways, strange to be asking an employee of a commercial company about the future of an open source software.</description></item><item><title>Quick tidyverse thoughts</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/quick_tidy_thoughts/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 15:38:18 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/quick_tidy_thoughts/</guid><description>There has been a lot of chatter about R and the tidyverse as of late - some of it prompted by Norm Matloff&amp;rsquo;s posts here and here.
Below you will find some quick thoughts on the topic. These are half-baked at best, and probably not fit for general consumption. This is mostly a way for me to get my thoughts down on the page.
The tidyverse has increased the approachability and accessibility of R to a large audience.</description></item><item><title>Data Science Minimalism</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/datasci_minimalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 11:42:51 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/datasci_minimalism/</guid><description>When I got my first taste of data science, it was intoxicating. With a few lines of code, I could visualize and explore data and make some inferences. I was drawn to data science by the possibilities it represented. The data science toolbox represented a key to unraveling the data I found all around me. Learning how to use these tools was exciting and made me feel powerful and capable.</description></item><item><title>Why workshops are tough to teach</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/workshops/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 09:39:47 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/workshops/</guid><description>A couple of weeks ago, I taught a one-hour workshop on the basics of writing functions in R. Overall, it went as well as I would expect an hour introduction workshop to go, which is to say OK but not great. Why not great? It turns out teaching skills in workshops is really difficult. But why?
I think it boils down to a couple of aspects of workshops:
Workshops:
are too short teach to the lowest skill level in the room don&amp;rsquo;t reflect how you actually learn these skill 1.</description></item><item><title>Good practices for working in R</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/r_best_practice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 16:16:50 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/r_best_practice/</guid><description>These are the slides from my presentation at the Colorado State University R Users Group on 4 Feb 2019
Good practices for working in R Guidelines, not rules Try to understand why you do each recommendation Know that you can break the rules Good, not best Best can be difficult to nail down Best depends on situation Obsession with &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; can interfere with the good Should you listen to me? &amp;hellip; or anyone for that matter?</description></item><item><title>Consulting</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/consulting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2018 16:43:02 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/consulting/</guid><description>Need help with something?
I currently consult on:
R
creating packages
data munging
profiling and optimizing code
Statistics
Bayesian analyses
Animal movement models: CSS, HMM, latent-state
Data Science</description></item><item><title>Retrospective Power Analysis</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/power/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 16:16:50 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/power/</guid><description>&amp;hellip;Or, can we trust these estimates? One of the most common questions that comes up in scientific publications is &amp;ldquo;Can I trust these conclusions?&amp;rdquo; Statistics is supposed to help us decide the weight of evidence for or against a certain conclusion, but there have been issues. We are realizing that the standard paradim is not holding up, and there are many more false positives in the literature than the p &amp;lt; 0.</description></item><item><title>Dynamic documents (part 2)</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/dyn_docs-pt2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 11:47:40 -0600</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/dyn_docs-pt2/</guid><description>Wow - long delay on this one. There are good reasons, which will be explained in coming posts. Stay tuned.
A brief intro to dynamic documents in R (cont.) Last time I outlined why you might want to use a dynamic document, and some of the popular formates that are commonly used. There are many great resources for the syntax used to actually create dynamic documents (e.g., for Rmarkdown: Rstudio, R-bloggers, etc.</description></item><item><title>Dynamic Docs in R (part 1)</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/dyn_docs-pt1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 11:14:04 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/dyn_docs-pt1/</guid><description>A brief intro to dynamic documents in R I was asked to give a short overview of dynamic documents in R during Dr. Cini Brown&amp;rsquo;s lab meeting at Colorado State University last week, and I thought I would post some of the material here as well.
What is a dynamic document? Dynamic documents, or living documents, are documents which can be continuously updated, and are often self-contained. This means that the document itself contains the framework to generate and update its content.</description></item><item><title>I blame Apple</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/keyboards/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 20:37:46 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/keyboards/</guid><description>I am a bit particular about keyboards. I find the keyboards on most computers to be trash, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a laptop or desktop. This has lead to our house having 3 quality mechanical keyboards, despite having only one desktop and one docking station (the odd one out, a classic 90&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;clicky&amp;rdquo; keyboard, was politely banned from our work space). This is also a reason I enjoy Lenovo laptops, as they tend to have better keyboards than most.</description></item><item><title>What I'm up to</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/update_nov30_2017/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:39:27 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/update_nov30_2017/</guid><description>I have been a bit quiet, mostly due to the holidays and general busyness. While I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything ready to go, there are some fun things coming down the line:
1. I have been converting the CA-Rice physiological model to Go.
Why this model? I reached out to Bard Miller, and he was kind enough to send the source code. I was pleasantly surprised to find that the code was simple, well-organized, and generally easy to make sense of.</description></item><item><title>Data science on the cheap - pt. 3</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 16:33:23 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap3/</guid><description>This is the last part of the series, and if you have not read the other two parts(pt. 1,pt. 2), it might be helpful to glance back to see how I got here.
In the last part, I explained the thinking that led me to build my own workstation using reclaimed parts. Here is brief overview of what I did:
Note: this is not intended to be a build guide. If you have no experience assembling a computer system, please find a beginner&amp;rsquo;s guide for the basics.</description></item><item><title>Data science on the cheap - pt. 2</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 17:09:12 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</guid><description>This is the continuation of Data Science on the Cheap, where I discussed the potential to use a Chromebook as a cheap entry to data science. After trying the main configurations, I concluded that the easiest use case was to use the Chromebook as a cheap and portable terminal to access a bigger machine elsewhere. But that leaves you with only half of the equation - you still need the other machine.</description></item><item><title>Forecasting famine during a food glut</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/food_glut/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 21:00:27 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/food_glut/</guid><description>Reuters just released a special story about the historic levels of food stocks, and the associated drop in agricultural profits, both at the farm and the farm services level. This is interesting to me because almost all of the papers I have written and the research I have done has been motivated by the need to produce more food to feed the growing population. Many influential papers in agriculture have highlighted the coming food shortages, the need to double food production by 2050, etc.</description></item><item><title>Data science on the cheap</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap_datasci/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 19:46:04 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap_datasci/</guid><description>One thing you will notice pretty quick if you hang around data-sci folks is they tend to pack pretty spendy hardware. During workshops, it is not uncommon for our classroom at the UC Davis Data Science Initiative to be packed full of Macbook Pros and other $1K+ laptops.
Recently my daily driver (Lenovo T460s) needed to go into the shop for a little work, which gave me a chance to play with my backup - a Lenovo Yoga 11e Chromebook, which I picked up for $160 shipped.</description></item><item><title>A few things I don't love about Stan</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/stan_gripes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 20:51:22 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/stan_gripes/</guid><description>First off, I love Stan. If you have not heard of Stan, I highly recommend you check it out. I use Stan for almost all of my statistics these days, and have published several papers using it.
That said, there are a fair number of things I don&amp;rsquo;t like about it:
The model trade-offs In my experience, when you are developing a model in Stan, you are often faced with trade-offs between 1) flexibility, 2) readability, and 3) development time.</description></item><item><title>Moving past p-values</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_v_old/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 19:35:44 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_v_old/</guid><description>I had a marathon review/revision session with my adviser last week regarding a manuscript I am working on - overall took 2 hours!
We were going round and round in circles, and finally 1.25 hours in we got to the piece of my paper that was really bugging my advisor: I did not have a single p-value in the entire paper. What followed was a really interesting exchange that I think highlights some of the issues that are behind scientific research, especially in agriculture, using out-of-date statistics.</description></item><item><title>What I study</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/research/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 18:17:59 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/research/</guid><description>Here is a collection of my published and unpublished work.
Publications Agriculture Rice yield improvements by through plant breeding are offset by inherent yield decreases declines over time. In prep. 2017.
Point stresses during reproductive stage rather than warming seasonal temperature determine yield in temperate rice. Glob Change Biol. 2017;00:1–10.
Variation in yield, starch, and protein of dry peas grown across Montana. Agronomy Journal, In Press, 2017
Yield gap analysis of US rice production systems shows opportunities for improvement.</description></item><item><title>Creating an R blog with Hugo (without using blogdown)</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/start/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 09:40:09 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/start/</guid><description>UPDATE: The fine folks behind Hugo put together a nice guild that covers the steps involved in getting github pages and Hugo setup.
I thought I would write up my experiences starting a blog that uses R code but that does not use blogdown. Why do I not use blogdown? The short story is that blogdown does not seem quite ready to use, as it is missing some elements to make publishing a blog easy.</description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 12:13:18 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/about/</guid><description>I am an agronomist (dealing with all things agriculture) by training, with an emphasis on the drivers of the yield of major crops. I am particularly interested in using the historic causes of yield variability to inform efforts to provide food, fuel, and fiber for our growing population sustainably.
But I wear many hats. I am also a data scientist, with a focus on increasing capability of researchers to expand what they can study.</description></item><item><title>Welcome</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/intro/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 21:03:33 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/intro/</guid><description>Hello World!
This is my first post to test out Hugo. Overall, it was a bit of a pain to set up with github personal pages. Oh well, it seems to be working now.</description></item></channel></rss>