<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ten thousand words...</title>
    <link>https://mespe.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ten thousand words...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 20:37:46 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mespe.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I blame Apple</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/keyboards/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 20:37:46 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/keyboards/</guid>
      <description>I am a bit particular about keyboards. I find the keyboards on most computers to be trash, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a laptop or desktop. This has lead to our house having 3 quality mechanical keyboards, despite having only one desktop and one docking station (the odd one out, a classic 90&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;clicky&amp;rdquo; keyboard, was politely banned from our work space). This has also a reason I enjoy Lenovo laptops, as they tend to have better keyboards than most.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m up to</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/update_nov30_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:39:27 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/update_nov30_2017/</guid>
      <description>I have been a bit quiet, mostly due to the holidays and general busyness. While I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything ready to go, there are some fun things coming down the line:
1. I have been converting the CA-Rice physiological model to Go.
Why this model? I reached out to Bard Miller, and he was kind enough to send the source code. I was pleasantly surprised to find that the code was simple, well-organized, and generally easy to make sense of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science on the cheap - pt. 3</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 16:33:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap3/</guid>
      <description>This is the last part of the series, and if you have not read the other two parts(pt. 1,pt. 2), it might be helpful to glance back to see how I got here.
In the last part, I explained the thinking that led me to build my own workstation using reclaimed parts. Here is brief overview of what I did:
Note: this is not intended to be a build guide.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science on the cheap - pt. 2</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 17:09:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</guid>
      <description>This is the continuation of Data Science on the Cheap, where I discussed the potential to use a Chromebook as a cheap entry to data science. After trying the main configurations, I concluded that the easiest use case was to use the Chromebook as a cheap and portable terminal to access a bigger machine elsewhere. But that leaves you with only half of the equation - you still need the other machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting famine during a food glut</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/food_glut/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 21:00:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/food_glut/</guid>
      <description>Reuters just released a special story about the historic levels of food stocks, and the associated drop in agricultural profits, both at the farm and the farm services level. This is interesting to me because almost all of the papers I have written and the research I have done has been motivated by the need to produce more food to feed the growing population. Many influential papers in agriculture have highlighted the coming food shortages, the need to double food production by 2050, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science on the cheap</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap_datasci/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 19:46:04 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap_datasci/</guid>
      <description>One thing you will notice pretty quick if you hang around data-sci folks is they tend to pack pretty spendy hardware. During workshops, it is not uncommon for our classroom at the UC Davis Data Science Initiative to be packed full of Macbook Pros and other $1K+ laptops.
Recently my daily driver (Lenovo T460s) needed to go into the shop for a little work, which gave me a chance to play with my backup - a Lenovo Yoga 11e Chromebook, which I picked up for $160 shipped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few things I don&#39;t love about Stan</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/stan_gripes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 20:51:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/stan_gripes/</guid>
      <description>First off, I love Stan. If you have not heard of Stan, I highly recommend you check it out. I use Stan for almost all of my statistics these days, and have published several papers using it.
That said, there are a fair number of things I don&amp;rsquo;t like about it:
The model trade-offs In my experience, when you are developing a model in Stan, you are often faced with trade-offs between 1) flexibility, 2) readability, and 3) development time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving past p-values</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_v_old/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 19:35:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_v_old/</guid>
      <description>I had a marathon review/revision session with my adviser last week regarding a manuscript I am working on - overall took 2 hours!
We were going round and round in circles, and finally 1.25 hours in we got to the piece of my paper that was really bugging my advisor: I did not have a single p-value in the entire paper. What followed was a really interesting exchange that I think highlights some of the issues that are behind scientific research, especially in agriculture, using out-of-date statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I study</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 18:17:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>Here is a collection of my published and unpublished work.
Publications Agriculture Rice yield improvements by through plant breeding are offset by inherent yield decreases declines over time. In prep. 2017.
Point stresses during reproductive stage rather than warming seasonal temperature determine yield in temperate rice. Glob Change Biol. 2017;00:1–10.
Variation in yield, starch, and protein of dry peas grown across Montana. Agronomy Journal, In Press, 2017
Yield gap analysis of US rice production systems shows opportunities for improvement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating an R blog with Hugo (without using blogdown)</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/start/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 09:40:09 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/start/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE: The fine folks behind Hugo put together a nice guild that covers the steps involved in getting github pages and Hugo setup.
I thought I would write up my experiences starting a blog that uses R code but that does not use blogdown. Why do I not use blogdown? The short story is that blogdown does not seem quite ready to use, as it is missing some elements to make publishing a blog easy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 12:13:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I am an agronomist (dealing with all things agriculture) by training, with an emphasis on the drivers of the yield of major crops. I am particularly interested in using the historic causes of yield variability to inform efforts to provide food, fuel, and fiber for our growing population sustainably.
But I wear many hats. I am also a data scientist, with a focus on increasing capability of researchers to expand what they can study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 21:03:33 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/intro/</guid>
      <description>Hello World!
This is my first post to test out Hugo. Overall, it was a bit of a pain to set up with github personal pages. Oh well, it seems to be working now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_v_old2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/new_v_old2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>