<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>computers on Ten thousand words...</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/categories/computers/</link><description>Recent content in computers on Ten thousand words...</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 15:19:41 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mespe.github.io/categories/computers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Workstation Update Pt. 2</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update_pt2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 15:19:41 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update_pt2/</guid><description>Previously, I discussed some of the reasons I was updating my computer, and what my goals for the rebuild would be - a smaller, quieter, more efficient, more powerful workstation.
There are many different ways to get to that goal. Here, I am going to talk through how I determined what path to take.
Processor This is probably the biggest determinate for the rest of the system, as it will dictate some of the other components.</description></item><item><title>Workstation Update</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 14:27:08 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/workstation_update/</guid><description>Way back in 2017, I built a cheap data science rig for $600. You can read about the build here. Since that post, I added a mid-tier NVIDIA GPU for machine learning, and some hard drives for more storage. Otherwise, it&amp;rsquo;s been pretty bullet-proof for the last 3 years.
While it was a great solution for what needed at the time, eventually it&amp;rsquo;s shortcomings were increasingly obvious. Those were:
Efficiency (or lack there of): 16 cores of 2012-circa Xeon processors pulled roughly 200W on their own.</description></item><item><title>I blame Apple</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/keyboards/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 20:37:46 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/keyboards/</guid><description>I am a bit particular about keyboards. I find the keyboards on most computers to be trash, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a laptop or desktop. This has lead to our house having 3 quality mechanical keyboards, despite having only one desktop and one docking station (the odd one out, a classic 90&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;clicky&amp;rdquo; keyboard, was politely banned from our work space). This is also a reason I enjoy Lenovo laptops, as they tend to have better keyboards than most.</description></item><item><title>Data science on the cheap - pt. 2</title><link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 17:09:12 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</guid><description>This is the continuation of Data Science on the Cheap, where I discussed the potential to use a Chromebook as a cheap entry to data science. After trying the main configurations, I concluded that the easiest use case was to use the Chromebook as a cheap and portable terminal to access a bigger machine elsewhere. But that leaves you with only half of the equation - you still need the other machine.</description></item></channel></rss>