<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Agriculture on Ten thousand words...</title>
    <link>https://mespe.github.io/tags/agriculture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Agriculture on Ten thousand words...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 16:16:50 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mespe.github.io/tags/agriculture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Retrospective Power Analysis</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/power/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 16:16:50 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/power/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;Or, can we trust these estimates? One of the most common questions that comes up in scientific publications is &amp;ldquo;Can I trust these conclusions?&amp;rdquo; Statistics is supposed to help us decide the weight of evidence for or against a certain conclusion, but there have been issues. We are realizing that the standard paradim is not holding up, and there are many more false positives in the literature than the p &amp;lt; 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m up to</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/update_nov30_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:39:27 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/update_nov30_2017/</guid>
      <description>I have been a bit quiet, mostly due to the holidays and general busyness. While I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything ready to go, there are some fun things coming down the line:
1. I have been converting the CA-Rice physiological model to Go.
Why this model? I reached out to Bard Miller, and he was kind enough to send the source code. I was pleasantly surprised to find that the code was simple, well-organized, and generally easy to make sense of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I study</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 18:17:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/research/</guid>
      <description>Here is a collection of my published and unpublished work.
Publications Agriculture Rice yield improvements by through plant breeding are offset by inherent yield decreases declines over time. In prep. 2017.
Point stresses during reproductive stage rather than warming seasonal temperature determine yield in temperate rice. Glob Change Biol. 2017;00:1–10.
Variation in yield, starch, and protein of dry peas grown across Montana. Agronomy Journal, In Press, 2017
Yield gap analysis of US rice production systems shows opportunities for improvement.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>