<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data science on Ten thousand words...</title>
    <link>https://mespe.github.io/categories/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data science on Ten thousand words...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 17:09:12 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mespe.github.io/categories/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science on the cheap - pt. 2</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 17:09:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap2/</guid>
      <description>This is the continuation of Data Science on the Cheap, where I discussed the potential to use a Chromebook as a cheap entry to data science. After trying the main configurations, I concluded that the easiest use case was to use the Chromebook as a cheap and portable terminal to access a bigger machine elsewhere. But that leaves you with only half of the equation - you still need the other machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data science on the cheap</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap_datasci/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 19:46:04 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/cheap_datasci/</guid>
      <description>One thing you will notice pretty quick if you hang around data-sci folks is they tend to pack pretty spendy hardware. During workshops, it is not uncommon for our classroom at the UC Davis Data Science Initiative to be packed full of Macbook Pros and other $1K+ laptops.
Recently my daily driver (Lenovo T460s) needed to go into the shop for a little work, which gave me a chance to play with my backup - a Lenovo Yoga 11e Chromebook, which I picked up for $160 shipped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few things I don&#39;t love about Stan</title>
      <link>https://mespe.github.io/post/stan_gripes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2017 20:51:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mespe.github.io/post/stan_gripes/</guid>
      <description>First off, I love Stan. If you have not heard of Stan, I highly recommend you check it out. I use Stan for almost all of my statistics these days, and have published several papers using it.
That said, there are a fair number of things I don&amp;rsquo;t like about it:
The model trade-offs In my experience, when you are developing a model in Stan, you are often faced with trade-offs between 1) flexibility, 2) readability, and 3) development time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>